Surprise!
Kejutan!
Alex. Do not interrupt me when I'm daydreaming.
Alex. Jangan ganggu jika aku sedang melamun.
When a zebra's in the zone, leave him alone.
Jangan ganggu jika aku sedang mengkhayal.
Come on, Marty. Just wanted to wish you a happy birthday.
Marty, aku hanya mau ucapkan selamat ulang tahun.
Hey, man, thanks.
Wah, terima kasih.
Hey, I got something stuck in my teeth.
Sesuatu terselip di gigiku.
It's driving me crazy. Can you help me? Please?
Menyebalkan. Tolong keluarkan, ya?
You came to the right place, my friend.
Kau minta tolong pada ahlinya.
Dr. Marty, D.D.S., is in the house.
Dr. Marty, DDS siap melayani.
Please hop on top of my sterilized examination table, if you may.
Silakan naik ke meja periksaku yang suci hama.
- [don't see anything. - It's on the left.
Tak ada apapun.!Sebelah kiri.
Oh, sorry.
Oh, maaf.
Okay, just don't talk with your mouth full.
Jangan bicara jika mulutmu penuh.
Right here. What the heck is this doing in there?
Ini dia. Mengapa ini ada di dalam mulutmu?
Happy birthday!
Selamat ulang tahun!
Aw, hey, thanks, man.
Oh, terima kasih, ya.
You put it in behind the tooth. You all right.
Kau taruh ini di belakang gigimu.
These aren't even on the shelf yet. Here. Check it out.
Ini bahkan belum dijual di kios suvenir.
- Look at that. Ooh! Look at that. - Look at that. It's snowing.
Lihat ini. Lihat itu.! Oh! Lihat itu. Hujan salju.
Ten years old, huh? A decade.
Umurmu 10 tahun? Satu dasawarsa.
Double digits. The big 1-0.
Dua digit. 1-0.
You don't like it?
Kau tak suka?
- No, no, it's great. - You hate it.
Suka sekali.!Kau benci.
I should've gotten you the Alex alarm clock. That's the big seller.
Harusnya kuberi jam alarm Alex. Suvenir paling laku.
No, no, no. The present's great, really.
Tidak. Aku suka ini, sungguh.
It's just that another year's come and gone
Aku hanya sedih, setahun berlalu...
and I'm still doing the same old thing.
hidupku masih tetap begini.
"Stand over here. Trot over there. Eat some grass. Walk back over here."
“Diam di sini. Berderap di sana. Makan rumput. Kembali ke sini."
- l see your problem. - Maybe I should go to law school.
Aku paham.! Harusnya aku kuliah Hukum.
You just need to break out of that boring routine.
Kau hanya harus lepaskan dirimu dari kejenuhan itu.
- How? - Throw out the old act.
Caranya?! Lakukan kebiasaanmu.
Who knows what you'll do. Make it up as you go along.
Entah apa yang akan kau lakukan.
Ad lib. Improvise. On the fly. Boom, boom, boom.
Improvisasi. Spontan. Lakukan yang tak terduga.
- Really? - You know, make it fresh.
Sungguh?Sesuatu yang segar.
Fresh, huh? Okay. I could do fresh.
Aku bisa lakukan yang segar.
Works for me.
Bagus.
Here come the people, Marty. I love the people.
Orang-orang datang, Marty. Aku suka orang.
It's fun people fun time!
Menyenangkan.
Let's go, Gloria! Up and at'em. We're open!
Ayo, Gloria! Bangun, mulai harimu yang baru! Kita sudah buka!
What day is it?
Hari apa ini?
It's Friday. Field trip day.
Hari Jum'at. Hari karyawisata.
Yes, it's field trip day. Let's get up and go...
Ya, hari karyawisata. Ayo hibur pengunjung...
..in ten more minutes.
10 menit lagi.
Come on!
Ayo!
Melman, Melman, Melman!
Melman, Melman, Melman!
Wake up! Rise and shine! It's another fabulous morning in the Big Apple.
Bangun! Ayo bersemangat! Ini pagi yang cerah di kota Apel Besar.
Let's go.
Ayolah.
- Not for me. I'm calling in sick. - What?
Aku tidak mau. Aku sakit.!Apa?
I found another brown spot on my shoulder. Right here. See?
Kulihat ada titik coklat lain di bahuku. Di sini. Lihat?
Right there. You see?
Di sana. Kau lihat?
Melman, you know it's all in your head. Hm?
Melman, itu hanya ada dalam pikiranmu.
Let's go! Come on!
Ayo masuk! Ayo!
Phil! Wake up, you filthy monkey.
Phil! Bangun, monyet jelek.
Oh, I'm going to be fresh.
Oh, aku akan segar.
Straight out the ground. Tasty fresh! Freshalicious.
Baru dipanen. Lezat dan segar! Segar dan sedap.
Ziploc fresh.
Segar sekali.
Ladies and gentlemen, children of all ages,
Saudara-saudara, anak-anak...
the Central Park Zoo proudly presents:
Kebun binatang Central dengan bangga persembahkan:
Show them the cat. Who's the cat?
Tunjukkan kehebatanku.
The king of New York City.
Raja Kota New York.
Alex the lion.
Alex sang Singa.
It's showtime.
Saat pertunjukan.
Roar!
Aum!
Gather around, people. Big show about to start.
Ayo berkumpul. Pertunjukan hebat segera dimulai.
Check out the zebra taking care of biz. That's right.
Lihat sang zebra melakukan aksinya! Ya, betul.
Just smile and wave, boys.
Ayo senyum dan melambai.
Smile and wave.
Senyum, melambai.
Kowalski, progress report.
Kowalski, beri laporan.
We're 500 feet from the main sewer line.
Kita sudah 500 kaki dari got utama.
- And the bad news? - We've broken our last shovel.
Kabar buruknya?! Sekop terakhir kita patah.
Right.
Ya.
Rico, you're on litter patrol. We need shovels.
Rico, cari sampah yang bisa dipakai. Kita perlu sekop.
And find more Popsicle sticks. We don't want to risk another cave-in.
Cari gagang es lilin yang banyak. Terowongan jangan runtuh lagi.
And me, skipper?
Aku, Skipper?
I want you to look cute and cuddly, private.
Harus tampak manis dan lucu, prajurit.
Today we're going to blow this dump.
Hari ini kita pergi dari sini.
Come here. Come here. Come on, penguin.
Kemari, kemari, ayo, Penguin.
Yeah! You don't see that on Animal Planet.
Kalian tak lihat itu di “Animal Planet.”
Ha-ha.
Ha-ha.
Well, show's over, folks. Thanks for coming.
Pertunjukan selesai. Terima kasih atas kedatangan kalian.
l hope you thought it was fresh.
Kuharap menurut kalian itu segar.
I'l be here all week.
Aku akan muncul sepanjang minggu.
In fact, I'll be here for my whole life.
Tepatnya seumur hidupku.
Three hundred and sixty-five days a year,
365 hari dalam setahun...
including Christmas, Hanukkah, Halloween, Kwanzaa.
termasuk hari Natal, Hanukkah, Halloween, Kwanzaa.
Please don't forget to never spay or neuter your pets.
Ingat, jangan pernah mengebiri hewan piara kalian...
And tip your cabbie, because he's broke.
dan berilah tip supir taksi karena dia tak punya uang.
You, quadruped. Sprechen sie Englisch?
Kau, kaki empat. Bisa bicara Inggris?
I sprechen.
Bicara.
- What continent is this? - Manhattan.
Benua apa ini?!Manhattan.
Hoover Dam! We're still in New York.
Bendungan Hoover! Kita masih di New York.
Abort. Dive! Dive! Dive.
Batalkan. Masuk kembali!
Hey. You in the tux. Wait a minute.
Kau yang memakai tuxedo. Tunggu.
What are you guys doing?
Apa yang kalian lakukan?
We're digging to Antarctica.
Menggali ke Antartika.
Ant-who-tica?
Antar-apa?
Can you keep a secret, my monochromatic friend?
Bisa pegang rahasia, hitam-putih?
Do you ever see any penguins running free around New York City?
Pernah lihat penguin berkeliaran bebas di kota New York?
Of course not. We don't belong here. It's just not natural.
Tentu tidak. Bukan tempat kami di sini. Ini bukan habitat kita.
This is all some kind of whacked-out conspiracy.
Kami di sini akibat komplotan jahat.
We're going to the wide-open spaces of Antarctica.
Kami mau kabur ke kawasan terbuka Antartika.
To the wild.
Kembali ke alam liar.
The wild? You could actually go there?
Alam liar? Kau sungguh dapat pergi ke sana?
That sounds great.
Terdengarnya menyenangkan.
Hey, hold up. Where is this place? Tell me where it is.
Sebentar. Di mana tempat itu? Di mana letaknya alam liar itu?
You didn't see anything.
Takkan kau ceritakan pada siapa pun.
Right?
Ya?
Yes, sir.
Siap, pak!
I'm sorry. No, sir.
Maksudku tidak akan.
For his final appearance of the day,
Untuk penampilan terakhirnya hari ini...
the king of New York City.
sang raja kota New York.
Alex the lion.
Alex sang singa.
Roar!
Aum!
Thank you. Thank you very much.
Terima kasih banyak.
You guys are great. You're a great crowd. Give yourselves a hand.
Kalian penonton yang baik. Tepuk tangan sendiri.
Thank you. Oh. Thank you.
Terima kasih. Terima kasih.
Oh! Well. Thank you.
Wah, terima kasih.
Oh, that's too kind. Too kind.
Kalian baik sekali. Terlalu baik.
Underpants!
Celana dalam!
Everybody get home safe. Hey! Check out my Web site.
Semoga selamat sampai di rumah. Hei! Lihat situsku.
Twenty-four hour Alex Cam. Watch me sleep.
Kegiatanku sepanjang hari. Lihat aku sedang tidur.
This is the life.
Ini baru namanya hidup.
That's the spot.
Ya, di situ.
Ohl! I'm in heaven.
Oh! Aku di sorga.
- Ooh, it's Marty's birthday. - Just rip it open.
Oh, ini ulang tahun Marty.! Sobek saja.
- What is it? - Come on. Open it up. What you got?
Apa ini, ya? Ayo dibuka. Apa isinya?
A thermometer.
Termometer.
Thanks. I love it, Melman. I love it.
Terima kasih. Aku suka ini, Melman. Aku suka.
l wanted to give you something personal. That was my first rectal thermometer.
Kuingin memberi yang pribadi. Itu termometer duburku yang pertama.
- Mother... - I'll miss that bad boy.
Brengs...!Akan aku rindukan.
Get the cake. Melman, come on.
Ambil kuenya. Melman, ayo.
Happy birthday to you
Selamat ulang tahun.
You live in a zoo
Kau tinggal di kebun binatang.
You look like a monkey
Tampangmu seperti monyet.
And you smell like one too
Baumu pun seperti monyet.
I say.
Menyebalkan.
Aw, well, now, you guys are just embarrassing me.
Aduh, kalian membuatku jadi malu.
And yourselves.
Permalukan kalian juga.
What? We worked on that all week.
Apa? Kami berlatih seminggu.
Let's go. Let's make a wish, babycakes.
Ayo. Sebutkan harapanmu, sayang.
- What'd you wish for? - Nope. Can't tell you that.
Apa harapanmu?Tak bisa kukatakan.
Come on. Tell.
Ayo katakan.
No siree. I'm telling you, it's bad luck.
Tidak akan, nanti bisa sial.
You want some bad luck, I'll blab it out.
Kalian ingin sial, akan kukatakan.
But if you want to be safe, I'll keep my mouth shut.
Jika ingin selamat, aku tutup mulutku.
Would you just tell us? What could happen?
Katakan apa yang bisa terjadi.
Okay.
Baik.
l wished I could go to the wild!
Kuharap aku bisa pergi ke alam liar!
The wild?!
Alam liar?
I told you it was bad luck.
Kataku juga, bawa sial.
The wild? Are you nuts?
Alam liar? Kau gila?
That is the worst idea I've ever heard.
Itu gagasan terburuk yang pernah kudengar.
It's unsanitary.
Jorok.
The penguins are going. So why can't I?
Penguin pergi, mengapa aku tidak?
The penguins are psychotic.
Para pinguin itu sinting.
Come on. Just imagine going back to nature.
Bayangkan kembali alam.
Back to your roots. Clean air, wide-open spaces!
Kembali ke asal. Udara segar, ruang luas terbuka!
I hear there's wide-open spaces in Connecticut.
Kudengar ada ruang terbuka di Connecticut.
- Connecticut? - You got to go over to Grand Central.
Connecticut?! Harus ke Stasiun Grand Central.
Then you got to take the Metro-North train... north?
Lalu naik kereta api Metro North ke utara?
So one could take the train? Just hypothetically.
Jadi bisa naik kereta api ke Connecticut? Hanya dugaan.
Come on. What would Connecticut have to offer us?
Apa yang bisa ditawarkan Connecticut pada kita?
- Lyme disease. - Thank you, Melman.
Penyakit Lyme.! Terima kasih, Melman.
No, I just want...
Aku cuma ingin...
There's none of this in the wild.
Di alam liar pasti tak ada ini.
This is a highly refined type of food thing
Ini jenis makanan canggih...
that you do not find in the wild.
yang takkan ada di alam liar.
You ever thought there might be more to life than steak, Alex?
Pernah terpikir ada yang lebih penting dalam hidup selain bistik?
He didn't mean that, baby. No, no, no.
Dia tak serius, sayang. Tidak.
Doesn't it bother you guys that you don't know anything
Tak terganggukah kalian, tidak tahu apa-apa tentang...
about life outside this zoo?
kehidupan di luar kebun binatang ini?
- Nuh-uh. Nope. -Mm-mm.
Tidak.fTidak.
Well, ! mean, come on. That's just one subject.
Jangan berlebihan, itu hanya satu masalah.
You got a little schmutz right there on your....
Ada sisa kue di wajahmu...
Thanks, guys. Thanks for the party. It was great.
Terima kasih, kawan-kawan, untuk pestanya. Menyenangkan sekali.
Really.
Sungguh.
What's eating him?
Mengapa dia?
Maybe you should talk to him. Go over and give him a little pep talk.
Bicaralah dengannya. Ke sanalah, beri semangat.
Hey, I already gave him a snow globe. I can't top that.
Dia sudah kuberi bola salju. Tak bisa lebih dari itu.
l can see where this is going.
Aku tahu ke mana ini arahnya.
It is getting late. I guess I'm going to...
Sudah malam. Rasanya aku mau...
Come on. He's your best friend.
Ayolah, dia sahabatmu.
All right, all right. Okay.
Baiklah, baiklah. Baik.
- Night, Marty. - Night, Glo.
Malam, Marty.!Malam, Glo.
What a day.
Hari yang menyenangkan.
I mean, I tell you, it just doesn't get any better than this, you know?
Kehidupan tak mungkin bisa lebih baik dari ini, ya?
Ooh! It just did. Even the star's out.
Oh! Baru saja lebih baik. Bahkan bintang bisa terlihat.
Not going to find a star like that in the wild.
Takkan bisa lihat bintang itu di alam liar.
Helicopter.
Itu helikopter.
Marty. Buddy. Listen.
Marty. Kawan.
Everybody has days when they think the grass might be greener somewhere else.
Dengar, siapapun alami saat-saat mengira rumput di tempat lain lebih hijau.
Alex.
Alex.
Look at me.
Lihat diriku.
I'm ten years old. My life is half over.
Umurku 10 tahun. Sudah kulewati setengah usia hidupku.
And I don't even know if I'm black with white stripes...
Tetapi aku belum tahu apakah aku ini hitam berbelang putih...
...or white with black stripes.
atau putih berbelang hitam.
Marty.
Marty.
I'm thinking of a song.
Aku jadi ingat sebuah lagu.
Alex. Please. Not now.
Alex. Jangan sekarang.
Oh, yes. It's a wonderful song. I think you're familiar with it.
Ini lagu yang indah. Kurasa kau pun mengenalnya.
Oh, no. Oh, no, you don't. No, no, no.
Oh, jangan. Jangan lagu itu.
I'm not listening.
Takkan kudengarkan.
Start spreadin' the news
Mulai sebarkan berita.
I don't know you.
Ini memalukan.
I'm leaving today
Aku akan pergi hari ini.
- We are a great big part of it - He's funny. Who is that?
Kita bagian besar dari kota itu.! Dia lucu. Siapa dia?
Come on. You know you know the words.
Ayo nyanyi, kau tahu liriknya.
Two little words.
Hanya dua kata.
New York.
New York.
Shut up, shut up, shut up! Hey, I'm sleeping here!
Diam, diam, aku sedang tidur!
We're not all nocturnal, you know!
Tak semua binatang malam!
I'll Knock your "turnal" right off, pal.
Aku bangunkan kau, kawan.
Yeah, you and what army, stripes?
Kau dan siapa, belang?
You mess with him, you mess with me, Howard.
Ancam dia berarti ancam aku, Howard.
- You're a bigmouth lion. - See? Mr. Grumpy Stripes.
Kau singa mulut besar.! Lihat? Tn. Belang Pengeluh?
We make a great team, the two of us.
Kita bisa jadi tim yang hebat.
We sure do. No doubt about it.
Percaya. Tak kuragukan.
So, what are you going to do? Go running off to the wild by yourself?
Lalu apa rencanamu? Mau kabur ke alam liar sendirian?
- No. - Good.
Tidak.JBagus.
You and me. Let's go.
Kau dan aku. Ayo.
- What? - The wild.
Apa?(Ke alam liar.
Come on. You and me together.
Ayo, kita berdua.
It's a straight shot down Fifth Avenue to Grand Central.
Kita naik kereta dari Stasiun Grand Central.
Weill grab a train, we'll head north.
Kita menuju utara.
We can be back by morning. No one will ever know.
Besok pagi sudah kembali, tak ada yang tahu.
You're joking. Right?
Kau bercanda, bukan?
Yeah. I'm joking. Of course I'm joking. Give me a break.
Ya, tentu aku bercanda. Memangnya kau bercanda?
Like we're going to get a train.
Masa kita naik kereta api.
Don't do that. You really had me worried there.
Jangan begitu, kupikir kau serius.
Oh, well. 1 guess I'll hit the sack.
Ya. Agaknya aku mau tidur saja.
Yeah, me too. I'll need to rest my voice for tomorrow.
Aku juga. Harus aku istirahatkan suaraku untuk besok.
It's Seniors' Day, you know. Have to roar extra loud.
Besok Hari Lansia. Harus mengaum lebih keras.
Give them a little jolt. You know?
Akan aku kagetkan mereka. Tahu, bukan?
Good night, AllyAl.
Selamat malam, AllyAI.
They forgot to turn off the ambience again.
Mereka lupa lagi mematikan kaset suara-suara hutan.
Don't worry. It's cool.
Jangan khawatir, biar aku.
You know, I got it.
Akan aku matikan.
Much better.
Jauh lebih baik.
Come on, now, baby.
Ayolah, sayang.
My little filet.
Filet-ku yang mungil.
My little filet mignon with a little fat around the edges.
Filet mignonku dengan sedikit lemak di pinggirannya.
like that. I like a little fat on my steak.
Aku suka itu. Sedikit lemak di bistikku.
My sweet, juicy steak. You are a rare delicacy.
Bistikku yang empuk dan lezat. Kau kenikmatan yang langka.
Alex. Alex. Alex!
Alex. Alex, Alex!
What? What?
Apa? Apa?
You suck your thumb?
Kau hisap jempolmu?
What is it, Melman?
Ada apa, Melman?
You know how I have that bladder infection
Saluran kemihku terinfeksi...
and I have to get up every two hours?
aku harus kencing tiap 2 jam.
I got up to pee and looked over at Marty's pen, which I usually don't do.
Saat kencing, kulihat ke kandang Marty, yang biasanya tak kulakukan.
I don't know why, but I did. And...
Entah mengapa kulakukan.
What? What's going on?
Apa yang terjadi?
It's Marty. He's gone.
Marty tidak ada.
Gone! What do you mean, "gone"?
Apa maksudmu tidak ada?
How long has he been working on this?
Sudah berapa lama dia lakukan ini?
Marty!
Marty!
He wouldn't fit down there.
Dia takkan muat di situ.
Marty? Marty! Marty!
Marty? Marty! Marty!
This doesn't make any sense. Where would he go?
Ini tak mungkin. Mau ke mana dia?
- Connecticut! - He wouldn't.
Connecticut!)Mustahil.
Oh, no! What are we going to do?
Oh, tidak! Apa yang harus kita lakukan?
I mean, we got to call somebody!
Kita harus minta bantuan!
Hello? Get me Missing Animals. And hurry.
Sambungkan dengan Hewan Hilang. Cepat.
We've got a lost zebra probably on the way to Connecticut, and we need...
Ada zebra hilang, mungkin sedang menuju Connecticut dan kami...
- Hello? Hello? - Wait a second.
Halo? Halo?Tunggu.
- We can't call the people. - What the...?
Jangan minta bantuan orang.!Apa?
They'll be really mad.
Mereka akan marah.
It'll get Marty transferred for good. Don't bite the hand that feeds you.
Marty bisa dipindahkan. Jangan gigit tangan yang beri makan kita.
Mm-hm, I know that's right.
Ya, benar.
We got to go after him. He's not thinking straight.
Kita susul dia. Pikirannya sedang kacau.
Let's stop him from making the biggest mistake of his life.
Cegah dia dari melakukan kesalahan terbesar dalam hidupnya.
He's probably out there lost and cold, confused.
Mungkin dia sedang tersesat, kedinginan dan kebingungan.
Poor little guy.
Kasihan dia.
Come on.
Ayo ikut.
One of us should wait here in case he comes back.
Harus ada yang diam di sini, kalau dia kembali.
Not now. This is an intervention. We all got to go.
Jangan pengecut. Kita semua harus pergi.
What's the fastest way to Grand Central?
Jalan tercepat ke Grand Central?
- You should take Lexington. - Melman!
Kau lewat Lexington.!Melman!
- Okay. "We." We should take Lexington. - What about Park?
Baik. “Kita” lewat Lexington.! Tidak lewat Park?
No, Park goes two ways. You can't time the lights.
Park jalan 2 arah, banyak lampu merahnya.
l heard Tom Wolfe is speaking at Lincoln Center.
Kudengar Tom Wolfe bicara di Lincoln Center.
Well, of course we're going to throw poo at him.
Tentu dia akan kita lempari kotoran.
We should've taken Park.
Seharusnya lewat Park.
You sure this is the fastest way to Grand Central Station?
Yakin ini yang tercepat ke Stasiun Grand Central?
I don't know! That's what Melman said.
Itu kata Melman.
Hey. Hey, you, guys.
Hei, kalian!
That room has some nifty little sinks you can wash up in, and look!
Kamar kecil itu wastafel kecilnya bagus, bisa cuci muka dulu, dan lihat!
Free mints!
Permen gratis!
This isn't a field trip.
Ini bukan wisata.
This is an urgent mission to save Marty from throwing his life away.
Ini misi penting mencegah Marty menghancurkan hidupnya.
Now, where's the train?
Mana keretanya?
Here it comes.
Itu dia.
What did Marty say to you? l asked you to talk to him.
Apa kata Marty? Kau aku minta bicara dengannya.
I did! I did! 1 don't understand. He said, "Let's go."
Sudah! Aku tak mengerti. Kata dia: "Ayo pergi.”
I said, "Are you crazy?" He says, "I'm ten years old."
Kataku:”Kau gila?” Kata dia: “Umurku 10 tahun.”
And he has black-and-white stripes, and so then we sang and...
Dan dia punya belang hitam dan putih, lalu kami menyanyi dan...
What you got to do is go straight back down West 42nd.
Kau harus putar balik lalu susuri West 42nd.
It's on your left after Vanderbilt.
Stasiun itu di kirimu setelah Vanderbilt.
If you hit the Chrysler Building, you've gone too far.
Jika sampai Gedung Chrysler berarti sudah terlewat.
Thanks a lot, officer.
Terima kasih, pak polisi.
Hey! Wait for the light.
Tunggu lampu hijau!
Freak.
Zebra aneh.
- Did you say "zebra"? - That's right. A zebra.
Katamu “zebra”?Betul. Zebra.
Right in front of me.
Di depanku.
- Can I shoot it? - Negative.
Boleh kutembak.'Tidak.
Then I'm going to need some backup.
Berarti aku perlu bantuan.
- Aw! Knicks lost again. - What are you going to do.
Knicks kalah lagi.Tindakanmu?
Did that say "Grand Central Station" or "my aunt's constipation"?
Katanya “Stasiun Grand Central” atau “bibiku mual”?
This is it.
Di sini.
Grand Central Station.
Stasiun Grand Central.
It's grand and it's central.
Memang megah dan di pusat kota.
Move aside. We have an emergency here. This is an emergency situation.
Minggir! Keadaan darurat. Ini keadaan darurat.
Hey, hey. Just chill out. It's not that big of an emergency.
Hei, hei, tenang. Ini bukan keadaan yang terlalu darurat.
Upstairs, downstairs.
Kuhantam di atas dan di bawah.
How do you like that?
Bagaimana rasanya?
Lady! What is wrong with you?
Nyonya! Kau ini mengapa?
Ow! Get a grip on yourselves, people.
Aduh! Tenanglah kalian.
You're a bad kitty.
Kucing nakal!
Dagnabbit! 1 missed the express.
Sial! Ketinggalan kereta itu!
Looks like I'll have to take the Stamford local.
Aku harus naik kereta Stamford.
I got him! I've got him!
Dia sudah kutemukan!
He's got him!
Sudah ditemukan!
He's got him! He's got...
Dia sudah ditemukan!
got something for you!
Ada sesuatu untukmu!
I'm okay. I'm okay.
Aku tak apa-apa.
Whoa! What are you guys doing here?
Mau apa kalian di sini?
- lam so glad we found you. - We were so worried about you.
Senang kau sudah ketemu.! Kami sangat cemaskan dirimu.
Don't worry, I'm fine, I'm fine. Look at me. I'm fine.
Aku baik-baik saja. Lihat diriku, aku baik-baik saja.
You're fine? Oh, he's fine. Oh, great.
Kau baik-baik? Dia baik-baik. Bagus.
You hear that? Marty's fine. That's good to know.
Kalian dengar? Marty baik-baik saja. Baguslah.
Because I was wondering...
Karena aku heran.
How could you do this to us? I thought we were your friends!
Teganya kau lakukan ini pada kami. Katanya teman!
What's the big deal? l was coming back.
Pokoknya aku sudah kembali.
Don't ever do this again. Do you hear me?
Jangan kau lakukan lagi, ya?
- Do you hear him? - Guys, we're running out of time.
Dengar katanya?! Sudah waktunya pulang.
Oh, Melman, you broke their clock?
Oh, Melman, kau rusak jam mereka?
...do this again! Don't you ever, ever do this again!
Jangan kau ulang! Jangan sekali lagi kau lakukan ini!
Come here.
Kemari.
We've been ratted out, boys.
Kita dikhianati.
Hold your fire!
Jangan tembak!
Cute and cuddly, boys. Cute and cuddly.
Muka manis dan lucu.
If you have any poo, fling it now.
Jika punya kotoran, lempar sekarang.
It's the Man.
Polisi.
Good evening, officers.
Selamat petang.
No. No. No. You don't talk now. Okay?
Jangan bicara sekarang. Mengerti?
You're not good with the “putting words together
Kau tak pandai menyusun...
and their coming out good" thing. You keep it "shh."
kata yang kesimpulannya bagus. Kau diamlah.
Hey! How you doing? You know what? Everything's cool.
Apa kabar? Semua baik-baik saja.
We just had a little situation here. Little internal situation.
Kami baru alami sedikit masalah. Masalah pribadi.
My friend went a little crazy. Happens to everybody.
Temanku hanya agak kacau. Bisa terjadi pada siapapun.
The city gets to us all. Went a little cuckoo in the head.
Kota ini membuat kami semua agak gila.
Don't be calling me cuckoo in the head.
Jangan sebut aku gila.
Just shush! I will handle this.
Diam kau! Biar aku tangani.
Ohl! I got him!
Aku dapat dia!
Go, go, go! Right here, please.
Cepat! Diam di sini.
Would you give a guy a break?
Hentikan mengganggu aku.
Weill take my little friend home and forget this ever happened. All right?
Akan kami bawa pulang temanku ini, kita lupakan saja semua ini, ya?
No harm, no foul, right?
Tak ada yang dirugikan.
Hey, it's cool. It's me, Alex the lion. From the zoo.
Jangan takut. Aku Alex, si singa. Dari Kebun Binatang.
What's the matter with them?
Mengapa mereka?
l feel really, really weird.
Aku merasa sangat aneh.
I love you guys.
Aku sayang kalian.
I love you so much.
Aku sangat sayangi kalian.
Last night's dramatic incident in Grand Central
Semalam kejadian dramatis di Grand Central...
is an example of what animal rights wackos have been shouting for years:
gambaran dari yang diteriakkan para militan hak-hak binatang.
Animals clearly don't belong in captivity.
Hewan-hewan itu jelas tak seharusnya dikurung.
They are to be sent back to their natural habitat,
Kini mereka akan dikembalikan ke habitat aslinya...
where they will live their lives in the freedom they desire.
hingga dapat hidup dalam kebebasan yang jelas diinginkan.
- Hey. Little help? - He's awake! He's awake!
Bisa bantu aku?Dia siuman!
Do something!
Lakukan sesuatu!
Oh, man.
Oh, tidak.
Oh, my head.
Oh, kepalaku.
What the...?
Apa yang terjadi?
Wait. Where? What?
Tunggu. Dimana aku? Apa?
I'm in a box! Oh, no. No, no! Not the box.
Aku di dalam kotak! Oh, tidak! Jangan di dalam kotak!
Oh, no, they can't transfer me. Not me!
Mereka tak boleh memindahkan bintang pertunjukan seperti aku!
Oh, I can't breathe. I can't breathe.
Aku tak bisa bernapas.
Darkness creeping in.
Aku mau pingsan.
I can't breathe. I can't breathe.
Aku tak bisa bernapas. Tak bisa napas.
Walls closing in around me.
Dinding merapat seputarku.
So alone. So alone.
Aku merasa begitu sendirian.
- Alex! Alex, are you there? - Marty?
Alex! Alex, kau di situ?!Marty.
- Yeah! Talk to me, buddy. - Oh, Marty! You're here!
Ya! Bicara padaku, teman.! Oh, Marty, kau di sini!
- What's going on? You okay? - This doesn't look good.
Kau baik-baik?Ini tidak baik.
- Alex, Marty, is that you? - Gloria!
Alex, Marty, itu kalian? 'Gloria!
- You're here too! - lam loving the sound of your voice.
Kau di sini juga!! Senang dengar suaramu.
- What is going on? - We're all in crates.
Apa yang terjadi? Kita di dalam peti.
Oh, no!
Oh tidak!
- Sleeping just knocks me out. - Melman!
Tidur membuatku tertidur.!Melman!
Is that Melman?
Itu Melman?
- Are you okay? - Yeah. No, I'm fine.
Kau baik?!Ya. Tidak, aku baik.
l often doze off while I'm getting an MRI.
Aku suka tertidur saat di-MRI.
- You're not getting an MRI. - CAT scan?
Kau tidak di-MRI.CAT-scan?
No CAT scan. It's a transfer. It's a zoo transfer.
Bukan. Kita dipindah ke kebun binatang lain.
Zoo transfer?! Oh, no. No, no, I can't be transferred.
Ke kebun binatang lain? Aku tak bisa dipindahkan.
l have an appointment with Dr. Goldberg at 5:00.
Janji dengan Dr.Goldberg jam 5.
There are prescriptions that have to be filled.
Ada resep yang harus dibuat.
No other zoo could afford my medical care.
Kebun binatang lain takkan mampu bayar.
And 1am not going HMO.
Aku tak mau pakai Askes.
Take it easy, Melman. It's going to be okay.
Tenang, Melman. Kita akan baik-baik saja.
- We are going to be okizay. - No, we're not going to be okizay.
Akan berez.! Kita tidak akan berez.
Now, because of you, we're ruined!
Gara-gara kau, kita celaka!
Because of me? fail to see how this is my fault.
Mengapa jadi gara-gara aku?
- You're kidding, right, Marty? - You. You ticked off the people.
Bercanda, bukan, Marty?7 Kau buat marah mereka.
You bit the hand, Marty. You bit the hand.
Kau gigit tangan yang memberimu makan.
"l don't know who I am. I got to go find myself in the wild." Oh, please.
“Harus kutemukan siapa diriku di alam liar.” Sudahlah.
I did not ask you to come after me, did I?
Tak aku minta menyusulku, bukan?
He does have a point.
Dia ada benarnya.
I did say we should stay at the zoo, but you guys...
Kataku kita tetap di kebun binatang saja, tetapi kalian...
Melman, just shut it.
Melman, diam.
You suggested this idea to him in the first place.
Gagasan naik kereta itu berasal darimu.
- Leave Melman out of this. - Thank you, Gloria.
Jangan libatkan Melman.! Terima kasih, Gloria.
Besides, it's not my fault that we were transferred.
Lagipula, bukan salahku kita dipindahkan.
Melman, shut it. Does anybody feel nauseous?
Melman, diam. Ada yang merasa mual?
- l feel nauseous. - Melman, you always feel nauseous.
Aku mual.!Melman, kau selalu merasa mual.
Progress report.
Laporan.
It's an older code, skipper. I can't make it out.
Ini sandi lama, Skipper, tak bisa aku pecahkan.
You, higher mammal.
Kau mamalia lebih tinggi.
Can you read?
Bisa baca?
No. Phil can read, though. Phil.
Tidak. Phil yang bisa. Phil.
Ship to Kenya.
Dikirim ke Kenya.
Wildlife preserve.
Suaka Margasatwa.
Africa!
Afrika!
Africa? That ain't going to fly. Rico.
Afrika? Itu tak boleh jadi, Rico!
I was the star in the greatest city on Earth.
Aku bintang di kota terbesar bumi.
- Guys, listen. - Aking. Loved by my people.
Dengarkan.! Aku raja. Dicintai rakyatku.
- Let's be civil. - And you've ruined everything!
Bersikap sopanlah. Kau rusak segalanya!
"Loved"?
“Dicintai”?
If the people loved you, it's only because they didn't know the real you!
Itu karena mereka tak tahu kau yang aslinya!
Don't make me come up there. I'll whoop both of yall.
Jangan memaksaku menghajar kalian.
I thought I knew the real you!
Kukira aku tahu kau yang asli.
Your black-and-white stripes, they cancel each other out. You're nothing!
Marty, belang hitam dan putihmu saling hapus. Kau bukan apa-apa!
Stop it, stop it, stop it!
Hentikan, hentikan!
You're not helping the situation.
Kalian memperburuk keadaan.
Status.
Status?
It's no good. I don't know the codes.
Tak baik, Skipper. Aku tak paham sandinya.
Don't give me excuses. Give me results! Navigation.
Jangan beri alasan. Beri hasil! Navigasi.
All right. Let me think.
Baik. Biarkan aku pikir.
And shut him up!
Dan suruh dia diam!
- I did it! - Let's get this tin can turned around.
Kutemukan sandinya!! Bikin kapal ini berputar.
Guys?
Kawan-kawan?
Oh, no.
Oh, tidak.
Gloria!
Gloria!
Melman!
Melman!
Marty!
Marty!
Alex!
Alex!
Marty?!
Marty?
Marty!
Marty!
No, wait. Come back, Marty!
Tunggu, Marty!
Don't go.
Jangan pergi.
Marty?
Marty?
Melman?
Melman?
Gloria?
Gloria?
Marty?!
Marty?
Melman?!
Melman?
Gloria?!
Gloria?
Marty!
Marty!
Melman! Gloria!
Melman! Gloria!
Hey, anyone! Hello!
Hei, siapa saja! Halo?
Marty, Melman, Gloria.
Marty, Melman, Gloria.
Gloria, Melman, Marty. Marty, Gelman, Gloria. Marty, Melman.
Gloria, Melman, Marty. Marty, Gelman, Gloria. Marty, Melman.
Morty, Morty, Gelman. Regis. Kelly.
Morty, Morty, Gelman, Regis, Kelly.
Matt, Katie, Al.
Matt, Katie, Al.
Get me out of this thing. Somebody. Hello?
Lepaskan aku dari ini. Siapa saja. Halo?
Get me out of this thing right now!
Lepaskan aku dari ini sekarang juga!
Hello? Somebody?
Halo? Siapa saja?
Melman!
Melman!
Alex? Is that you?
Alex? Kaukah itu?
Melman, I got you. Hang on! Hang on. I got you.
Melman, kau akan kutolong. Diam! Diam! Akan kutolong.
Melman! I got you, buddy.
Melman! Kau akan kutolong, kawan.
Wait a sec, Melman. Wait right there.
Tunggu, Melman. Tunggu di situ.
- What are you doing? - I'm getting you out of the box.
Apa yang kau lakukan?! Mengeluarkanmu.
- Relax. - Alex?
Tenang.!Alex?
Giraffe, corner pocket!
Jerapah, kantung pojok!
Here goes nothing!
Satu-satunya jalan.
- Wait, wait, wait, wait. - Hold still!
Tunggu, tunggu.'Diam.
- Wait, Alex. - Hold still.
Tunggu, Alex.!Diam.
- No, come on. - Here I come!
Jangan, tunggu.!Aku datang!
Look! Look! Look! Look!
Lihat! Lihat! Lihat!
It's Gloria. It's Gloria!
Itu Gloria. Itu Gloria!
Oh, hey, it is Gloria.
Hei, itu Gloria.
Oh, my...
Astaga...
Gloria!
Gloria!
Alrighty, boys, fun's over.
Kawan-kawan, sudah cukup.
Alex!
Alex!
- Marty?! - Marty!
Marty?!Marty!
Yeah! All right! That's right!
Ya! Asyik! Bagus!
Left! Left! Left. No, no, your left! Your left! Your left!
Kiri! Kiri! Kiri. Bukan, kirimu! Kirimu!
Right here's good.
Berhenti di sini.
I don't have anything on me right now. I'll have to get you later.
Aku tak bawa uang sekarang. Kalian akan aku bayar lain kali.
To you too.
Sampai jumpa juga.
Marty!
Marty!
Alex!
Alex!
All
Al!
Marty!
Marty!
Alex?
Alex?
Oh, sugar, honey, ice tea.
Oh, sial.
Martin!
Martin!
- Hold up! - I'm going to kill you!
Tunggu!Kubunuh kau!
- Come here! Don't run away from me! - Calm down!
Kemari! Jangan lari dariku!Tenang!
If you keep running, I'm going to just kill you more!
Jika kau lari terus, aku makin marah!
Oh, look at us.
Oh, lihatlah kita.
We're all here together. Safe and sound.
Kita semua di sini. Aman dan selamat.
Yeah, here we are.
Ya, kita disini.
Where exactly is "here"?
Tetapi tepatnya dimana?
San Diego.
San Diego.
San Diego?
San Diego?
White sandy beaches,
Pantai pasir putih...
cleverly simulated natural environment, wide-open enclosures.
lingkungan alam tiruan yang sempurna, kandang terbuka.
I'm telling you, this could be the San Diego Zoo.
Mungkin ini Kebun Binatang San Diego.
Complete with fake rocks.
Lengkap dengan batuan palsu.
Wow, that looks real.
Wah, seperti sungguhan.
San Diego? What could be worse than San Diego?
San Diego? Apa yang lebih buruk dari San Diego?
I don't know. This place is crackalacking!
Entah. Tempat ini lumayan.
Oh, I could hang here. l could hang here.
Aku bisa hidup di sini. Bisa tinggal di sini.
- I'll kill you! - Take it easy!
Kubunuh kau!Tenang!
- Strangle you! - Calm down.
Kucekik kau!fTenang.
Then bury you, dig you up, clone you and kill your clones.
Lalu aku kubur kau, kugali lagi, kujiplak lalu kubunuh semua jiplakanmu!
- 20-second timeout. - I'll never talk to you again.
Istirahat 20 detik.! Aku tak mau bicara denganmu lagi.
Now, look. We're just going to find the people,
Kita cari petugas disini...
get checked in and have this mess straightened out.
kita mendaftar lalu kita bereskan kekacauan ini.
Oh, great. This is just great. San Diego.
Bagus, bagus sekali. San Diego.
Now I'll have to compete with Shamu and his smug little grin.
Kini aku harus bersaing dengan si paus Shamu dan senyum angkuhnya.
I can't top that. Can't top it.
Aku tak bisa mengalahkannya.
I'm ruined! I'm done. I'm out of the business.
Aku hancur! Tamat! Karirku tamat!
It's your fault, Marty! You've ruined me.
Gara-gara kau, Marty! Kau hancurkan karirku.
Come on, Alex. Do you honestly think
Sudahlah, Alex. Kau pikir...
l intended all of this to happen?
semua ini aku sengaja terjadi?
You want me to say that I'm sorry? Is that what you want?
Kau ingin aku katakan menyesal?
Okay, I'm...
Baiklah, aku...
He just shushed me.
Dia suruh aku diam.
Marty, look, you've got to be just a little bit more und...
Marty, kau harus agak lebih pengerti...
- Don't you shush me. - Do you hear that? Don't you hear that?
Jangan suruh aku diam.! Kalian dengar itu? Dengar itu?
- hear it now. - Where there's music, there's people.
Sekarang aku dengar. Ada musik, ada orang.
- Go to the head honcho. - A sidewalk would be nice.
Kita temui kepalanya.! Coba ada kaki limanya.
Yeah, what a dump.
Tempat brengsek.
They should call it the San Di-lame-o Zoo.
Harusnya namanya Kebun Binatang San Di-payah.
First they tell you, "We got this great open plan thing. Let animals run wild."
Pasti mereka akan bilang: "Hewan-hewan bebas berlarian disini.”
Next thing, flowers in your hair, everybody's hugging everybody.
Tahu-tahu, ada bunga di rambutmu dan semua saling berpelukan.
This place kind of grows on you. This way, guys! Come on!
Tempat ini makin menyenangkan. Ayo lewat sini, kawan-kawan.
What the...?
Astaga...!
Oh, no!
Oh, tidak!
Okay, let's make a good impression on the people.
Ayo beri kesan baik pada para petugas.
Smiles, everyone. Let's get it together.
Senyum, semua. Bersikap tenanglah.
- ls that the best you can do? - Oh, I'm not smiling. It's gas.
Itu senyum terbaikmu?! Bukan senyuman, aku sakit perut.
Well, great. Let's make gas look good.
Senyum sakit perutmu yang bagus.
- Wow! - It's not people. It's animals.
Wahljltu bukan orang, itu hewan.
California animals. Dude.
Hewan-hewan Kalifornia.
This is like a Puffy party.
Seperti pesta Putffy.
I like to move it, move it
Kuingin menari, menari.
- Ya like to - Move it
Kau akan suka.!Menari.
I like to move it, move it You like to move it, move it
Kau ingin menari, menari.
She like to move it, move it
Dia suka menari, menari.
- He like to - Move it
Dia suka.!Menari.
All girls all over the world
Semua gadis di seluruh dunia...
Original King Julien ‘pon yer case, man
King Julien asli akan ceritakan.
I love how all the girls that love to move their body
Aku suka semua gadis yang suka menari.
When ya move your body, ya do
Jika kau menari...
Move it nice and sweet and sassy, all right
gerakkan tubuhmu yang seksi.
What kind of zoo is this?
Kebun binatang macam apa ini?
I just saw 26 blatant health code violations.
Aku lihat 26 pelanggaran standar kesehatan.
I'm loving San Diego. This place is off the chizain.
Aku suka San Diego, tempat ini asyik.
Twenty-seven.
27.
Woman, physically fit, physically fit
Wanita tubuhnya sehat, tubuhnya sehat, tubuhnya sehat.
Physically, physically, physically fit Physically fit, Physically fit
Tubuhnya sehat, tubuhnya sehat.
We should've brought chips and dip.
Harusnya bawa makanan ringan.
Wait.
Tunggu.
Where's Alex? What happened to him? He was right behind us. Wasn't he?
Mana Alex? Apa yang terjadi? Tadi di belakang kita. Ya, bukan?
I don't know where he's at, but he's missing one heck of a party.
Entah di mana dia, dia lewatkan pesta asyik.
The foosa!
Kucing foosa!
The foosa are attacking! Run for your lives!
Foosa menyerang! Selamatkan nyawamu!
- Foosa hungry. - Foosa eat.
Foosa lapar.!Foosa makan.
l hate spiderwebs.
Aku benci jaring laba-laba.
Yeah, thanks a lot, guys.
Terima kasih, kawan-kawan.
Thanks for waiting up. Really appreciate it.
Terima kasih menungguku. Aku hargai itu.
Hey, hi. We just got in from New York, and we're looking for a supervisor.
Hai. Kami baru tiba dari New York, kami cari pak kepala.
Because we've been sitting on that beach back there for hours,
Berjam-jam kami duduk di pantai...
and nobody's even bothered to show up.
tak ada yang menyambut kami.
I don't know how things are normally run around here,
Entah bagaimana cara kerja di sini...
but there's been some sort of major screwup, which is cool.
tetapi ada kekacauan besar yang menyenangkan.
So if you could point us towards the administrative offices, we'll...
Tunjukkan saja di mana kantor pak kepala, biar kami...
Well, howdy-do.
Apa kabar?
Spider! Spider! Spider on my back!
Laba-laba! Laba-laba! Di punggungku!
Maurice, did you see that?
Maurice, kau lihat itu?
He scared the foosa away.
Dia membuat takut foosa itu.
Come on, Gloria. Get it.
Ayo, Gloria, hajar.
Get it! Get it! Get it!
Hajar! Hajar!
- That's it! Smack it! - Get it, get it!
Bagus, Gloria! Hantam!)Habisi!
Whip it! Whip it good! Where'd it go?
Sikat habis! Ke mana dia?
King Julien, what are they? What are they?!
King Julien, makhluk apa itu? Apa mereka itu?
They are aliens. Savage aliens from the savage future.
Mereka dari luar angkasa. Makhluk buas dari masa depan yang buas.
They've come to kill us. And take our women. And our precious metals.
Mereka mau bunuh kita. Merampas wanita kita. Logam berharga kita.
Get up, Mort. Do not be near the king's feet, okay?
Berdiri, Mort. Jangan dekat-dekat kaki Raja.
We're hiding. Be quiet, everyone. Including me.
Kita sembunyi. Jangan bersuara, semua. Termasuk aku.
Who's making that noise?
Suara siapa itu?
Oh, it's me again.
Suaraku lagi.
There it is! Get it! Come on, Gloria!
Itu dia! Habisi! Ayo, Gloria!
- Enough! Enough with the stick. - [ think she got it.
Cukup memukuliku dengan itu.! Kurasa sudah mati.
Is it still on me? I hate spiders.
Masih padaku? Aku benci laba-laba.
It's okay. It's gone.
Sudah pergi.
They are savages.
Mereka makhluk buas.
Tonight we die.
Kita mati.
The feet. I told you... I told you to... I told every...
Jangan di kakiku. Sudah kubilang, kubilang.
Didn't I tell him about the feet?
Sudah kubilang, bukan?
He did tell you about the feet.
Dia pernah bilang soal kaki.
- Wait. I have a plan. - Really?
Tunggu. Aku punya rencana.Sungguh?
l have devised a cunning test
Sudah kutemukan tes yang cerdik...
to see whether these are savage killers.
untuk memastikan apakah mereka itu pembunuh.
Hi there.
Halo.
You let me handle it. Alex handles it. Marty does nothing.
Biar aku tangani. Alex tangani. Marty diam saja.
Hi there.
Halo.
Oh, jeez. Sorry.
Astaga. Maaf.
- Oh, Alex, what'd you do? - Stop. Stop. It's okay. It's okay.
Oh, Alex, apa yang kau lakukan?! Jangan menangis lagi Tidak apa-apa.
I'm just a silly... Just a silly lion. Oh, jeez!
Aku cuma singa bodoh. Ampun!
- Aw, Alex! - Oh, you poor little baby.
Alex!Oh, anak malang.
Did that big mean lion scare you?
Singa besar jahat itu menakutimu?
He did? He's a big, bad old puddy tat, isn't he?
Begitu? Dia kucing besar tua jahat, ya?
Come on. Mamai'll hold you. Aww, look at you.
Ayo, Mama akan mendekapmu. Oh, lihat dirimu.
They are so cute from a reasonable distance.
Mereka lucu, dilihat dari jauh.
Aren't you the sweetest little thing. I just want to dunk him in my coffee.
Kau lucu sekali. Ingin rasanya mencelupmu dalam kopiku.
They're just a bunch of pansies.
Mereka cuma sekawanan banci.
I don't know.
Entahlah.
There's something about that one with the crazy hairdo
Aku curiga pada yang dandanan rambutnya aneh itu...
that I find suspicious.
yang aku curigakan.
Nonsense, Maurice.
Kau ada saja, Maurice.
Come on, everybody. Let's go and meet the pansies!
Ayo semua, kita temui banci-banci itu.
Presenting your royal highness, our illustrious King Julien XIll,
Perkenalkan Yang Mulia Baginda kami Raja Julien XIII...
self-proclaimed lord of the lemurs, et cetera. Hooray, everybody.
yang menyatakan dirinya penguasa kaum lemur, dan sebagainya. Hore, semua!
He's got style.
Dia punya gaya.
What is he, like, king of the guinea pigs?
Seperti apa dia, Raja Marmot?
I think it's a squirrel.
Kurasa itu bajing.
Welcome, giant pansies.
Selamat datang, banci-banci raksasa.
Please feel free to bask in my glow.
Silahkan menikmati kemegahanku.
- Definitely a squirrel. - Yep. Squirrel.
Pasti bajing.Ya, bajing.
We thank you with enormous gratitude for chasing away the foosa.
Terima kasih sekali kalian halau foosa itu.
- The "whossa"? - The foosa.
Foo-apa?Foosa.
They annoy us by trespassing, interrupting our parties
Mereka menjengkelkan, suka ganggu pesta kami...
- and ripping our limbs off. - Good.
dan mencincang kami.!Baguslah.
We're just trying to find out where the people are, so...
Kami hanya mau bertemu para petugas, jadi kalau...
What big teeth you have. Man!
Besar sekali gigimu, Man.
Shame on you, Maurice. Can you not see that you have insulted the freak?
Malulah, Maurice. Tak sadarkah sudah kau hina si aneh itu?
You must tell me, who the heck are you?
Katakan, siapa kalian ini?
I'm Alex. The Alex. And this is Gloria, Marty and Melman.
Aku Alex yang ternama. Ini Gloria, Marty dan Melman.
And just where are you giants from?
Kalian raksasa-raksasa dari mana?
We're from New York and...
Dari New York dan...
All hail the New York giants!
Semua, hidup raksasa New York!
New York giants!
New York Giants!
Is this some sort of inbreeding program?
Ini semacam program pembauran?
Il say we just got to ask these bozos where the people are.
Tanyakan pada idiot-idiot ini di mana semua orang?
Excuse me. We bozos have the people, of course.
Kami para idiot pemilik semua orang, tentu.
Hey, the bozos have the people.
Para idiot pemilik semua orang.
Oh, well, great. Good. Phew.
Oh ya, bagus. Baik.
They're up there.
Mereka di atas.
Don't you love the people? Not a very lively bunch, though.
Tak sayang pada orang? Mereka tampaknya tak semangat.
Wow.
Wah.
So do you have any live people?
Ada orang yang masih hidup?
No. Only dead ones.
Hanya yang sudah mati.
l mean, if we had a lot of live people here,
Jika di sini banyak manusia hidup...
it wouldn't be called the wild, would it?
ini takkan disebut daerah liar, bukan?
The wild?
Daerah liar?
Whoa. Hold up there a second, fuzzbucket.
Tunggu dulu sebentar, ember bulu.
You mean, like,
Maksudmu...
the "live in a mud hut, wipe yourself with a leaf" type wild?
jenis liar yang diam di gubuk tanah liat yang cebok pakai daun?
- Who wipes? - Oy vey.
Siapa yang cebok?!Ya, ampun.
- Oy vey! - Oy vey, everybody!
Ya, ampun!!Ya, ampun semua!
Oy vey!
Ya, ampun!
Could you excuse me for a moment?
Permisi sebentar.
Get me out of here! We got to get out of here!
Kita harus pergi dari sini!
- Help! - What are you doing?!
Tolong!Apa yang kau lakukan?
I'm swimming back to New York.
Aku mau berenang ke New York!
I know my chances are slim, but I have to try!
Aku tahu peluangku kecil, tetapi harus aku coba!
- You can't swim! - l said my chances are slim!
Kau tak bisa berenang.Aku tahu.
Nature! It's all over me! Get it off! can't see! I can't see!
Alam! Di sekelilingku! Singkirkan! Aku tak bisa melihat!
Il can see!
Aku bisa melihat!
Look. There's obviously just been a little mistake.
Dengar. Jelas ada kekeliruan kecil.
The people didn't dump us here on purpose.
Kita tak sengaja dibuang di sini.
As soon as they realize what happened, they'll come looking for us, right?
Begitu mereka tahu yang terjadi, akan mencari kita.
Yeah, right.
Betul.
I don't know the words But we're born free
Aku tak tahu liriknya tetapi kita terlahir bebas.
You know something? I bet they're already on their way.
Pasti mereka sedang kemari untuk menyelamatkan kita.
Well, boys, it's going to be ice-cold sushi for breakfast.
Kita akan sarapan sushi dingin.
Rico.
Rico.
Well, since I'm doomed to die on this forsaken island,
Karena aku akan mati di pulau terpencil ini...
], Melman Mankiewicz,
aku, Melman Mankiewicz...
being of sound mind and unsound body,
dalam keadaan pikiran sehat dan fisik tak sehat...
have divided my estate equally among the three of you.
tanah milikku sudah kubagi rata di antara kalian bertiga.
Sorry, Alex.
Maaf, Alex.
Hey! A latrine. Nice work, Melman. Outdoor plumbing.
Hei! Lubang kakus. Kerja bagus, Melman. Kakus tempat terbuka.
No, it's not a latrine.
Itu bukan lubang kakus.
It's a grave. You sent Melman to his grave. Are you happy?
Itu liang kubur. Gara-gara kau, Melman mati muda. Kau senang?
Aw, come on.
Ah, konyol.
This isn't the end. This is a whole new beginning.
Ini bukan akhir. Ini awal baru dari kehidupan kita.
This could be the best that's happened.
Mungkin hal terbaik yang kita alami.
No. No. No. No.
Tidak, tidak, tidak.
No. No. No. No. No. No. This is not the best thing that's happened to us.
Tidak, tidak. Ini bukan hal terbaik yang terjadi pada diri kita.
You abused the power of the birthday wish and brought bad luck on all of us.
Kau langgar kekuatan harapan ulang tahun hingga kita semua dapat sialnya.
Why'd you tell your wish? You're not supposed to.
Mengapa kaukatakan harapanmu? Itu bawa sial.
I didn't want to tell you. Remember?
Aku tak ingin, ingat?
- You guys made me tell you. - Oh, okay.
Kalian yang memaksaku mengatakannya.Baiklah.
Besides, this isn't bad luck. This is good luck.
Lagipula, ini bukan kesialan, ini keberuntungan.
Look around. There's no fences, no schedules.
Lihat sekelilingmu. Tak ada pagar, tak ada jadwal.
This place is beautiful. Baby, we were born...
Ini tempat yang indah.
Okay. Okay. I've had enough of this.
Baiklah, aku tak mau dengar lagi.
This is your side of the island, and this is our side of the island.
Sisi ini wilayah pulaumu, sisi ini wilayah pulau kami.
That is the bad side, where you can prance and skip
Itu sisi yang buruk, kau boleh loncat-loncat...
like a magical pixie horse and do whatever the heck you want.
seperti kuda ajaib, melakukan apapun sesukamu.
This is the good side for those who love New York and care about going home.
Ini sisi baik bagi yang mencintai New York dan ingin kembali.
- Come on. - No, no. Back! Back!
Yang benar.! Jangan. Mundur! Mundur!
You know what? This isn't good.
Ini tidak baik.
Okay! You all have your side, and I'll have mine.
Baiklah! Kalian di sisi kalian dan aku di sisiku.
And if you need me, I'll be over here,
Jika perlu aku, aku ada disini...
on the fun side of the island, having a good old time.
di sisi gembira pulau ini, bersenang-senang.
This is the fun side,
Ini sisi yang gembira...
where we'll have a great time surviving until we go home.
kami akan senang sampai saatnya pulang.
- A yabbadabbado old time! - This side's the best.
Saat yabba-dabba-do!) Ini sisi terbaik.
That side stinks! You're on the Jersey side of this cesspool!
Sisi itu bau! Kau ada di sisi kubangan limbah!
- Wilma! - Now what do we do?
Wilma!Lalu apa?
Don't worry. I have a plan to get us rescued.
Aku punya rencana untuk diselamatkan.
Can't wait to see the look on Marty's face when he sees this.
Aku tak sabar ingin lihat muka Marty saat melihat ini.
Just look at him. He's helpless without us.
Lihat saja dia. Tak berdaya tanpa kita.
Shut up, Spalding.
Diam kau, Spalding.
I've been standing here for hours, man.
Sudah berjam-jam aku disini.
How long do I have to pose like this?
Harus berapa lama lagi?
She is finito.
Sudah selesai.
I defy any rescue boat within a million miles
Aku jamin kapal penyelamat sejauh 1 mil dari sini...
to miss this baby.
pasti bisa lihat ini.
When the moment is right, we will ignite the beacon of liberty
Pada saar yang tepat, kita nyalakan obor kebebasan ini.
and be rescued from this awful nightmare!
dan kita akan diselamatkan dari mimpi buruk ini.
What do you think? Pretty cool, huh?
Apa pendapatmu? Bagus, bukan?
- How's the liberty fire going, Melman? - Great. Idiot.
Bagaimana api kebebasannya, Melman?Baik. Bodoh.
I heard that.
Aku dengar itu.
Why can't we just borrow some of Marty's fire?
Mengapa kita tak pinjam api Marty saja?
That's wild fire. We're not using wild fire on Lady Liberty.
Itu api liar. Takkan kita pakai untuk nyalakan Nona Kebebasan.
- Now, rub, Melman. - I've been doing...
Ayo gosok, Melman.fltu kulakukan.
I can't. l can't. I can't do it. I ju... l can't do it!
Tetapi tak mau menyala. Pokoknya aku tak bisa bikin api.
Fire.
Api.
Fire! Fire!
Api! Api!
Oh, my
Astaga.
Fire!
Api!
Not yet! No, no! No!
Jangan dulu! Jangan!
Melman, hold still!
Melman, diam!
Jump! Alex, jump!
Loncat! Alex, loncat!
Don't worry, cats always land on their...
Jangan takut, kucing selalu mendarat...
Face? Man, what kind of cat are you?
Di mukanya? Kucing macam apa kau ini?
You maniac!
Kau gila!
You burned it up!
Kau bakar patungku!
Darn you!
Sial kau!
Darn you all to heck!
Sial dangkalan, kau!
Can we go to the fun side now?
Kita bisa ke sisi gembira sekarang?
Everybody, calm down. Come on. Into your chairs.
Semua tenang. Ayo duduk lagi.
Let go of his tail.
Semua tenang. Lepaskan ekornya.
Separate those two, would you, please?
Tolong pisahkan mereka berdua.
You here, you there. Everyone...
Kau disini, kau disana. Diam.
Now, presenting your royal highness, the illustrious blah, blah, blah.
Kini aku persilakan yang mulia baginda dan seterusnya.
You know, et cetera, et cetera. Hooray. Let's go.
Kalian tahu, dan sebagainya. Hore! Ayo.
Now, everybody,
Kita semua...
we all have great curiosity about our guests, the New York giants.
penasaran soal tamu kita, para raksasa New York itu.
- Yes, Willie? - like them.
Ya, Willie?!Aku suka mereka.
I like them. I liked them first. Before ! even met them I liked them.
Aku yang suka lebih dulu, bahkan sebelum bertemu mereka.
I liked them right away. You hate them compared to how much I like them.
Langsung suka. Dibanding sukaku, kau bisa dikata benci mereka.
Oh, shut up. You're so annoying!
Diam kau, menyebalkan.
Now, for as long as we can remember,
Nah, sepanjang ingatan kita...
we have been attacked and eaten by the dreaded foosa.
kita selalu diserang dan dimakan oleh foosa.
The foosa! The foosa are attacking!
Foosa! Foosa menyerang!
It's a cookbook! It's a cookbook!
MEMASAK LEMUR
Please. Maurice.
Diam, Maurice.
Quiet!
Diam!
Come on, y‘all. They're not attacking us this very instant.
Jangan panik. Foosa takkan langsung menyerang.
So my genius plan is this:
Rencana jeniusku begini:
We will make the New York giants
Para raksasa New York itu...
our friends and keep them close.
jadikan teman, biarlah tinggal di sini.
Then, with Mr. Alex protecting us,
Dengan perlindungan Tn. Alex...
we will be safe and never have to worry
kita akan aman tak perlu takut...
about the dreaded foosa ever again.
pada foosa lagi.
I thought of that. I thought of that. Yes. Me. I did.
Itu buah pikiranku. Betul, itu gagasanku.
Hold on, everybody. Hold on. I'm just thinking now.
Tunggu dulu. Baru terpikir olehku.
I mean, does anyone wonder why the foosa
Terpikirkah mengapa foosa...
were so scared of Mr. Alex?
begitu takut pada Tn. Alex?
l mean, maybe we should be scared too.
Mungkin harusnya kitapun takut.
What if Mr. Alex is even worse than the foosa?
Bagaimana jika Tn. Alex lebih jahat dari foosa?
I tell you, that dude just gives me the heebiedabajeebies.
Terus terang, dia membuat perasaanku terganggu.
Maurice, you did not raise your hand.
Maurice, kau tak angkat tangan.
Therefore, your heinous comment will be stricken from the record.
Sebab itu, komentar jahatmu akan dicoret dari catatan.
Does anyone else have the heebie-jeebies?
Siapa lagi yang merasa terganggu?
No? Good. So shut up.
Tidak ada? Bagus. Jadi, diam.
When the New York giants wake up,
Jika para raksasa itu bangun...
we will make sure that they wake up in paradise.
kita pastikan mereka seperti bangun di sorga.
Now, who would like a cookie?
Siapa yang mau kue?
Yo, Al. Melman and Gloria are over there having a good time.
Hei, Melman dan Gloria ada di sana sedang senang-senang.
There's room on the fun side for one more.
Masih ada tempat satu lagi.
No, thanks.
Tidak, terima kasih.
Look, I've been thinking. Maybe if you gave this place a chance,
Kupikir, jika kau lebih berpikiran terbuka akan tempat ini...
I don't know, you might even enjoy yourself.
mungkin kau pun akan senang.
Marty, I'm tired. I'm hungry.
Marty, aku lelah dan lapar.
I just want to go home.
Aku hanya ingin pulang.
Could you just give it a chance? Think about it.
Berilah kesempatan lagi. Pikirkan dulu.
It really isn't the fun side without you.
Sungguh tak senang tanpa kau.
I know. And then...
Aku tahu. Tetapi...
- It's him. - Who is it?
Itu dia.Siapa itu?
It's the pizza man. Who the heck do you think it is?
Pengantar pizza. Kau pikir siapa?
Yes? Can I help you?
Ya? Bisa aku bantu?
Can I come to the fun side?
Boleh aku ke sisi gembira?
Beg your pardon?
Apa?
You know, I've been kind of a jerk.
Aku memang menyebalkan.
But I've been thinking about what you said, and I'm sorry.
Tetapi sudah kupikirkan ucapanmu, aku minta maaf.
Welcome to Casa del Wild. Take a load off.
Selamat datang di Wisma Liar. Duduklah.
Hey, hey, wipe your feet.
Hei, bersihkan dulu kakimu.
- Alex! - Mi casa is su casa.
Alex!! Rumahku adalah rumahmu.
Very impressive.
Hebat sekali.
Hey, have a drink. It's on the house.
Minumlah. Gratis.
This is seawater.
Ini air laut.
Oh, you don't swallow it. It's just temporary till the plumbing's done.
Jangan ditelan. Hanya untuk sementara sampai ledengnya beres.
Hey, y'all look hungry.
Kalian tampak lapar.
How would you like some of nature's goodness?
Mau makanan alam yang lezat?
You have food?
Kau punya makanan?
The Fun Side Special, coming up.
Hidangan spesial Sisi Gembira.
Seaweed on a stick.
Sate rumput laut.
Seaweed?
Rumput laut?
On a stick. Don't love it till you try it.
Sate. Jangan dicela sebelum dicoba.
That's unbelievable.
Ternyata enak.
- So good. - Well, thanks.
Enak sekali.fTerima kasih.
It does kind of hit the spot, doesn't it?
Agak mengenyangkan, bukan?
Well, maybe it could use a little lemon.
Mungkin lebih enak pakai limau.
No, it's great. It's really great. Doesn't get any better than this.
Sudah enak. Enak sekali. Tak ada yang lebih baik dari ini.
Oh, but it does.
Hidup bisa lebih baik.
Check this out.
Lihat ini.
Wow. Would you look at that.
Wah. Coba lihat itu.
It's like billions and billions of helicopters.
Seperti bermilyar-milyar helikopter.
It's a shooting star. Make a wish. Quick!
Bintang jatuh. Mintalah sesuatu. Cepat!
Ooh! How about a thick, juicy steak?
Boleh minta bistik yang tebal dan empuk?
You know what, Alex?
Alex...
I promise you I'm going to find you a steak tomorrow if it kills me.
janji akan aku dapatkan besok untukmu biarpun aku harus mati.
Thanks, Marty.
Terima kasih, Marty.
It is getting late. I guess I'm going to...
Sudah malam, aku mau...
I think I'm going to hit the sack too.
Aku pun mau tidur.
Sweet dreams, everyone.
Selamat mimpi, semuanya.
Alex.
Alex.
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Twenty-seven, 28, 29. Thirty black and only 29 white.
27, 28, 29. 30 hitam dan hanya 29 putih.
Looks like you're black with white stripes after all.
Ternyata kau ini hitam dengan belang putih.
Dilemma solved. Good night.
Dilema terpecahkan.
You see, Maurice, Mr. Alex was grooming his friend.
Kau lihat, Maurice. Tn. Alex mendandani temannya.
He is clearly a tender, loving thing.
Jelas dia itu berhati lembut.
How can you have the heebie-jeebies for Mr. Alex?
Mengapa kau merasa terganggu melihat Tn. Alex?
Look at him. He's so cute and plushy.
Lihat dia. Begitu manis dan berbulu lembut.
I don't think he was grooming him.
Bukan mendandani.
Look more like he was tasting him to me.
Mungkin bersiap mau memangsanya.
Suit yourself, no matter. I don't care.
Terserah, tak jadi soal. Masa bodoh.
Soon we will put my excellent plan to action.
Kita akan segera melaksanakan rencanaku yang hebat.
All we have to do is wait
Kita hanya harus menunggu...
until they are deep in their sleep.
sampai mereka tidur lelap.
How long is this going to take?!
Akan berapa lama menunggunya?
Well, this sucks!
Ini menyebalkan.
Wake up, Mr. Alex.
Bangun, Tn. Alex.
Rise and shining.
Hari sudah pagi.
Wakey-waking, Mr. Alex!
Ayo bangun, Tn. Alex.
Wake up! Alex!
Bangun! Alex!
You suck your thumb?
Kau hisap jempolmu?
Where are we? What the heck is going on?
Kita di mana? Apa yang terjadi?
Where's the beach? Take it easy.
Mana pantai itu?fTenang.
- Who built a forest? - Don't be alarmed, giant freaks.
Siapa yang bikin hutan?7 Jangan kaget, raksasa aneh.
While you were asleep,
Saat kau tidur...
we simply took you to our little corner of heaven.
kami pindahkan ke sorga kecil kami.
Welcome to Madagascar.
Selamat datang di Madagaskar.
- Mada-who-ah? - What?
Mada-apa?Apa?
No, not whooha. Ascar.
Bukan Mada-apa, Madagaskar.
Marty. It's...
Marty, ini...
Just like my mural back at the zoo.
Persis lukisan tembok di kandangku dulu.
Oh, no, fella, that is the real deal right there.
Bukan lukisan, kawan, ini yang sebenarnya.
Look at that, that's not a bad view.
Lihat, itu bukan pemandangan buruk.
That's the thing that you were always looking at, but it's actually there.
Itu persis lukisan tembokmu, tetapi ini yang sebenarnya.
- That's the real version of... - How about once around the park?
Itu versi aslinya...! Ayo lihat sekeliling.
Let's get our blood pumping, lungs breathing this fresh air.
Ayo kita pompa darah kita, paru-paru kita diisi udara segar ini.
Who's with me?!
Siapa mau ikut?
Naw. I don't think I could... You're it!
Aku tidak bisa... Kejar aku!
Hey! Want to play around?
Hei! Mau bergembira?
Got you there!
Kena kau!
Come here!
Kembali!
You're it.
Kau jadi.
Hey, stop that! Hey, you're crazy!
Hei, hentikan! Kau sudah gila?
Okay, Marty, I'm it.
Baiklah, Marty, aku kalah.
I'm it. I'm it. You win.
Aku kalah, kau menang.
Come on, Alex, get in the groove.
Ayolah, Alex, semangat sedikit.
l haven't eaten in two days.
Sudah 2 hari tidak makan.
My blood sugar's real low. I just don't have the energy.
Gula darahku rendah. Tak ada tenaga.
I don't think that's your problem.
Bukan itu masalahnya.
First of all, that's not how you run in the wild.
Bukan begitu cara lari di alam liar.
Let's go. Put the rubber to the road!
Ayo. Lari secepat-cepatnya!
You just have to let out that inner lion.
Lepaskan singa liar dalam dirimu.
- Now, who's the cat? - Marty, I really don't...
Ayo siapa singa yang hebat?! Ini bukan gagasan yang baik.
You are, that's who. Come on! Here we go!
Kau singa yang hebat. Ayo! Lari!
That's it. Let's build up some steam! You the cat.
Bagus. Tingkatkan kecepatanmu. Kau kucing hebat.
- Who's the cat? - You the cat.
Siapa singa yang hebat?Kau.
Who's the cat? Who's the cat?
Siapa yang hebat? Siapa yang hebat?
I'm the cat!
Aku singa yang hebat!
Surprise!
Kejutan!
You're it. You're it!
Kau jadi!
Can't juke the cat. Cat's too quick.
Tak bisa kalahkan singa. Singa terlalu cepat.
l feel like a mile-high pastrami on rye on the fly from the deli in the sky!
Aku merasa seperti pastrami setinggi 1 mil dari langit!
- Let's go wild! - Now you're talking!
Ayo berlaku liar!J Itu baru benar!
Man! I feel different.
Wah! Aku meresa beda.
Noogie, noogie, noogie. Noogie, noogie, noogie!
Nugie, nugie, nugie, nugie!
Kind of charged up or something.
Energiku serasa meningkat cepat!
- Like you said, baby, it's... - Crackalacking.
Seperti katamu, tempat ini...!Lumayan.
- Ain't that right, Melman? - Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah.
Betul, Melman?Oh, ya. Oh, ya.
I'm in heaven.
Aku di sorga.
You see, Maurice, Alex is now our friend and the foosas are nowhere to be seen.
Maurica, kini Alex teman kita, foosa tak nampak batang hidungnya.
It could be said that my plan is working
Boleh dikata rencanaku berhasil...
in a very good working kind of way.
dengan baik sekali.
Alex. You got to try some of this.
Alex. Kau harus coba makan ini.
I feel good. Feel like a king again.
Aku merasa nyaman. Serasa jadi raja lagi.
King?
Raja?
You should see his act.
Kau harus lihat pertunjukannya.
Come on, Alex, why don't you show him some of your act.
Ayo, Alex, tunjukkan padanya.
Oh. No, I really don't think I could... Okay.
Oh tidak, aku tidak bisa... Baiklah.
Ladies and gentlemen. Primates of all ages.
Hadirin semua. Primata segala usia.
The wild proudly presents:
Alam liar dengan bangga persembahkan:
The king.
Sang Raja!
Alex the lion!
Alex sang Singa!
E flat, fellas.
E flat, kawan-kawan.
Yeah! The king is in the house!
Ya! Sang raja sudah tiba!
See, if he is the king, then where is his crown? I've got a crown.
Jika dia raja, mana mahkotanya? Aku punya mahkota.
Got a very nice one. And it's here on my head.
Mahkotaku bagus sekali. Di kepalaku.
Look at it. Have I got it on?
Lihat. Sudah aku pakai?
Do the roar, man. Do the roar.
Ayo mengaum. Mengaum.
Wow. I've never heard that one before.
Belum pernah aku dengar sekeras itu.
Yeah! Go wild, man! Come on!
Ya! Ayo yang liar! Ayo!
Break out the wave!
Pecahkan gelombang!
Excuse me.
Maaf.
You're biting my butt.
Kau gigit bokongku.
- No, I'm not. - Yes, you are.
Tidak.Ya, kau gigit.
- What did you do? - You just bit me!
Apa yang kau lakukan?! Kau gigit aku!
No. I didn't. Did I?
Aku tidak menggigit.
You kind of did.
Kau gigit.
What the heck is wrong with you?
Mengapa kau lakukan itu?
Why'd you bite me?
Mengapa gigit aku?
- Man, it's because you are his dinner. - What?!
Karena kau makanannya.!Apa?
- Excuse me? - That's dumb.
Apa?Tak mungkin.
Come, come, Maurice. What is a simple bite on the buttocks among friends?
Sudah, Maurice. Apalah gigitan kecil di bokong sesama teman?
Here, give me a nibble.
Ini, gigit bokongku.
The party is over, Julien. Your brilliant plan has failed.
Pesta selesai, Julien. Rencanamu gagal.
What are you talking about?
Apa maksudmu?
Your friend here is what we call
Temanmu itu yang disebut...
a deluxe-model hunting and eating machine.
model mewah mesin berburu dan makan.
And he eats steak...
Dia makan bistik...
. which is you.
alias kau.
- Get out of here. - Okey-dokey, Maurice, I admit it.
Bercanda.Baik, Maurice. Aku akui.
The plan failed.
Rencanaku gagal.
All is lost! We're all doomed.
Kita semua dalam bahaya.
The foosas will come back and gobble us with their mouths because...
Foosa akan kembali untuk melahap kita karena...
...we are all steak.
kita semua daging bistik.
I'm steak! Me, me, me!
Aku bistik! Aku, aku!
Mr. Alex cannot stay here.
Tn. Alex tak bisa tinggal di sini.
He belongs with his own kind on the foosa side of the island.
Dia harus tinggal dengan jenisnya di daerah foosa pulau ini.
By the power vested in me,
Atas nama hukum yang diberikan padaku...
by the law of the jungle, blah, blah, blah, blah...
hukum rimba, dan seterusnya...
Be gone!
Pergi!
What? Come on, do! look like a steak to you?
Apa? Apa aku mirip bistik di matamu?
Yeah!
Ya!
See, I told you I don't look like a... Wait. What you say?
Sudah kukatakan aku tak mirip... Tunggu. Apa katamu?
Oh, yeah!
Oh, ya!
- He's going savage. - Run for your lives.
Dia jadi buas.!Selamatkan nyawamu!
Marty, run!
Marty, lari!
A bull's eye. Excellent shot, Maurice.
Tepat. Tembakan bagus, Maurice.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Marty?
Marty?
I'm so sorry, Marty.
Aku sungguh menyesal, Marty.
What is wrong with me?
Apa yang salah dengan diriku?
Ow.
Aduh.
Oh, no.
Oh, tidak.
What have I done?
Apa yang telah aku lakukan?
It's true. I'm a monster.
Ternyata benar. Aku ini monster.
I got to get out of here.
Aku harus pergi dari sini.
What have I done? This is a nightmare.
Apa yang telah kulakukan? Ini mimpi buruk.
And it's all my fault.
Semua ini salahku.
Now, because of me, we've lost Alex.
Karena aku, kita kehilangan Alex.
Well, what are we going to do?
Apa tindakan kita?
Weill find a way to help him. That's what we'll do.
Kita cari akal untuk menolongnya.
Okay.
Baiklah.
Come on, we are New Yorkers, right?
Kita warga New York, bukan?
We're tough. We're gritty.
Kita ini tangguh, kita ini ulet.
We're adaptable!
Bisa menyesuaikan diri.
And we are not going to lay down like a bunch of Melmans.
Takkan menyerah seperti sekawanan Melman!
No, we're not.
Kita tidak begitu.
Oh. Gloria.
Oh, Gloria.
That was not me, okay? That was the boat.
Bukan suara perutku. Itu suara kapal.
- The boat! - The boat?
Kapal!!Kapal?
The boat's come back for us! Come on, guys, we got to flag it down.
Kapal itu kembali untuk kita! Ayo beri isyarat.
There it is!
Itu dia!
- Hey, over here! - Over here!
Hei, di sini!JDi sini!
Over here! Yo!
Di sini! Yo!
Melman, give me a lift. Hurry up! Lift me up!
Melman, angkat aku ke atas. Cepat!
Help! Help! Help!
Tolong! Tolong!
- Oh, my neck. My neck. You guys. - Over here!
Aduh, leherku. Leherku sakit! IDi sini!
- Melman! Steady. This way! - You have no idea how much this hurts.
Melman! Diamlah!! Kau tak tahu betapa sakitnya.
Hey, boat! We're over here!
Hei, kapal! Kami di sini!
Look! It's turning! It's coming back! It's coming back!
Lihat! Berputar! Kapal itu kembali! Kapal kembali!
Come on! Come on, baby!
Kemari! Kemari, sayang!
Yes! You guys.
Ya! Kawan-kawan.
You flag down that boat. I'll get Alex.
Beri isyarat! Akan kucari Alex.
Whoa! Hold on there.
Tunggu! Jangan pergi.
You cannot go back there by yourself.
Kau tak bisa ke sana sendirian.
Aw, come on. I know Alex.
Aku tahu Alex.
He hears we're rescued, he'll snap right out of it.
Jika tahu kita diselamatkan, dia akan baik lagi.
The people are coming. They can help us.
Orang-orang datang. Mereka dapat menolong kita.
Melman's right. The people will Know what to do.
Melman benar. Mereka tahu harus bagaimana.
Now, we got to flag down that boat.
Kita harus beri tanda.
Now, this is more like it.
Ini lebih bagus.
You?! Oh, ma... Where are the people?
Kau? Astaga. Mana orang-orangnya?
We killed them and ate their livers.
Kami bunuh, kami makan hatinya.
Got you, didn't I?
Tertipu, ya?
Just kidding, doll, the people are fine.
Cuma bercanda, cantik, mereka baik-baik saja.
They're on a slow lifeboat to China.
Mereka naik pelampung ke Cina.
Hey, I Know you two.
Hei, aku tahu siapa kalian.
Where's that psychotic lion and our monochromatic friend?
Mana singa sinting dan teman kita si hitam-putih itu?
Marty? He's righ... Where did he go? He was right behind us.
Marty? Kemana dia? Tadi di belakang kita.
He went back for Alex. He's going to get himself killed!
Dia mencari Alex. Pasti akan dimangsa Alex!
Well, boys, our monochromatic friend's in danger.
Teman hitam-putih kita dalam bahaya.
Looks like we have a job to do.
Dia harus kita selamatkan.
Captain's log: Embarking into hostile environment.
Catatan Kapten: Mendarat di wilayah yang bermusuhan.
Kowalski. We'll need to win the hearts and the minds of the natives.
Kowalski. Kita harus merebut hati penduduk pribumi.
Rico. We'll need special tactical equipment.
Rico. Kita perlu peralatan taktis spesial...
We're going to face extreme peril.
untuk menghadapi bahaya.
Private probably won't survive.
Serdadu mungkin takkan selamat.
Alex! Come out, Alex!
Alex! Keluarlah, Alex!
The boat's here! We can go home!
Kapal datang! Kita bisa pulang!
Alex! Alex! Alex! Alex! Alex!
Alex! Alex! Alex! Alex!
Alex! Alex! Alex!
Alex! Alex! Alex!
Alex!
Alex!
Marty?
Marty?
Snap out of it, Alex. The boat came back. We can get out of here.
Sadarlah, Alex. Kapal sudah datang. Kita bisa pergi dari sini.
We can go back to civilization, and everything will be like it used to be.
Kita kembali ke peradaban, semua pulih seperti semula.
Stay back.
Menjauh dariku.
Please.
Aku mohon.
I'm a monster.
Aku ini monster.
Alex, you're no monster. You're my friend.
Alex, kau bukan monster. Kau sahabatku.
We're a team. You and me, remember?
Kita ini tim. Kau dan aku, ingat?
I don't want to hurt you.
Aku tak ingin menyakitimu.
Alex.
Alex.
l ain't leaving without you.
Aku takkan pergi tanpa kau.
Alex? I'm thinking of a song.
Alex? Aku ingat sebuah lagu.
It's a wonderful song. I'm sure you're familiar with it.
Lagu bagus. Aku yakin kau tahu lagu itu.
Start spreadin' the news
Mulailah sebarkan berita.
I'm leaving today
Aku akan pergi hari ini.
We are a great big part of it
Kita bagian besar dari kota itu.
Come on, you know the words. Two little words.
Ayolah, kau tahu liriknya. Dua patah kata.
Please don't make me sing this by myself.
Jangan biarkan aku menyanyi sendirian.
You really don't want to hear me sing this by myself.
Kau pasti tak ingin dengar aku nyanyikan sendirian.
Uh, Alex? Could you come out here for a minute?
Alex, bisa keluar ke sini sebentar?
Hey, Alex, a little help.
Hei, Alex, tolong aku.
Help me!
Tolong aku!
Alex! Help!
Alex! Tolong!
Help me! Anybody, help me! Somebody!
Siapa saja, tolong! Siapa saja!
Help!
Tolong!
- Melman? - That's right, baby.
Melman?Ya betul, sayang.
Run!
Lari!
- What's the plan? - This is the plan.
Apa rencananya7fIni rencananya.
- Foosa hungry. - Foosa eat.
Foosa lapar.!Foosa makan.
This is the plan?
Ini rencananya?
Foosa halt.
Foosa berhenti.
Foosa ooh.
Foosa ooh.
Foosa aaahh.
Foosa aah.
Come and get it.
Ayo makan.
Foosa.
Foosa.
- Take that. - Foosa ow!
Rasakan itu.!Foosa aduh!
There's too many of them, skipper.
Mereka terlalu banyak, Skipper.
It's been a real pleasure serving with you boys.
Senang bertugas bersama kalian.
Alex?
Alex?
That's my kill.
Itu mangsaku.
Mine.
Milikku.
Alex hungry.
Alex lapar.
Alex eat.
Alex makan.
It's showtime.
Saatnya pertunjukan.
Thanks for not giving up on me.
Terima kasih kau kembali untukku.
Man, you almost gave me a heart attack. You can't just come sneak up on me.
Aduh, aku kaget sekali. Jangan menyergapku seperti itu.
Just because you're a lion... Let go of me. Let go of me.
Mentang-mentang kau singa. Lepaskan aku, lepaskan.
We're getting out of here. Guys, just go with me on this.
Kita akan pergi dari sini. Kalian ikuti saja rencanaku.
Like I said, it's showtime.
Seperti kataku, saatnya pertunjukan.
Mine.
Milikku.
My kill.
Mangsaku.
They're all mine.
Semua mangsaku.
It's the king of the beasts! Oh, no!
Raja hewan! Oh, tidak!
- Don't eat me! - He's big and scary!
Jangan makan aku, Tn. Singa.'Takut!
Fear me! Savagery beyond comprehension.
Takuti aku! Keganasanku tak terbayangkan!
- lam far too young to die! - You're a monster! A monster, I say!
Aku terlalu muda untuk mati.! Kau monster! Monster!
- And, you! - Me?
Dan kau!)Aku?
Oh, you want some of this? Ooh! You better run for your lives.
Mau makan ini? Sebaiknya lari, selamatkan nyawamu.
- Somebody call a cop! - He's psychotic!
Panggil Polisi!)Dia sinting!
This is my territory. Understand?
Ini wilayahku. Mengerti?
I never, ever want to see you on my turf again.
Aku tak mau melihatmu di wilayahku lagi.
Boo.
Pergi.
Yeah! You the cat!
Ya! Kau singa hebat!
Got my boy back!
Alex-ku sudah normal lagi!
I did it!
Aku berhasil!
Give me some love! The plan worked! The plan worked! I'm very clever!
Pujilah aku! Aku berhasil! Aku pintar sekali!
I'm the one, baby! Come on. Time to robot.
Aku yang terhebat! Ayo! Saatnya dansa robot.
lam very clever king.
Aku raja yang pintar.
lam super genius.
Aku jenius super.
lam robot king of the monkey things.
Aku raja robot dari bangsa mirip monyet.
- Compute, compute. - So, what's for lunch?
Hitung, hitung.! Kita makan siang apa?
- Close those eyes. - Why do I have to?
Tutup matamu.!Mengapa?
- Do it. - They're closed.
Lakukan.Sudah.
- Tighter. - Yes, sir.
Lebih rapat.Ya, pak.
- No peeking. - They're closed.
Jangan mengintip.'Sudah rapat.
Rico.
Rico.
Hai.
Siap.
Open that hatch.
Buka mulutmu.
Fire in the hole. Now chew.
Api di lubang. Kunyah.
Chew like you mean it. Savor it.
Kunyah seolah kau menikmatinya.
- And? - Well?
Dan?)Enakkah?
Pretty good, right?
Enak sekali?
There's always Plan B.
Selalu ada rencana cadangan.
This is better than steak.
Lebih enak dari bistik.
love it. I love it!
Aku suka sekali.
The kitty loves the fishy.
Kucing itu suka ikan.
Well, I propose a toast.
Ayo bersulang.
Now, he may be a pain in the butt at times...
Mungkin kadang dia menjengkelkan...
And trust me, I know.
Percayalah, aku tahu.
But this cat proved to me without a doubt
Tetapi singa itu membuktikan...
that his heart is bigger than his stomach.
hatinya lebih besar dari perutnya.
- To Alex.
Untuk Alex.! Untuk Alex.
Enough! Stop it!
Cukup! Hentikan!
What do you think? Should we head back to New York?
Bagaimana? Kita pulang ke New York?
I don't know. I mean, this is your dream.
Entah. Ini impianmu.
You sure you want to leave?
Sungguh kau ingin pulang?
I don't care where we are.
Masa bodoh kita di mana.
As long as we're together, it doesn't matter to me.
Asal kita berkumpul bersama.
Well, in that case...
Kalau begitu...
Yo. Rico. I'll take 300 orders to go.
Rico, aku minta 300 sushi untuk dibawa.
Hai.
Siap.
But before you leave, l have an announcement to make.
Tetapi sebelum kau pergi, aku ada pengumuman.
So shut up, everyone, please. Thank you.
Jadi diamlah semua. Terima kasih.
After much deep and profound brain things inside my head,
Setelah kugodok sampai matang di otakku dalam kepalaku...
l have decided to thank you
aku putuskan berterima kasih...
for bringing peace to our home.
padamu bawa perdamaian di kawasanku.
And to make you feel good,
Agar kau merasa enak...
I'm going to give you this lovely parting gift.
kuberikan hadiah perpisahan ini.
No, I couldn't. Really, I can't take your crown.
Jangan, sungguh. Tak bisa aku ambil mahkotamu.
That's okay, I've got a bigger crown.
Tak apa, aku punya yang lebih besar.
It's got a gecko on it.
Ada tokeknya.
Look at him shake. Go, Stevie, go!
Lihat dia bergoyang. Tunjukkan, Stevie!
- Bye, little fuzzbuckets! - Thanks for everything!
Selamat tinggal.! Terima kasih segalanya.
- So long! - Bye-bye, now.
Sampai jumpa.Selamat jalan.
- Arrivederci. - Bye-bye.
Selamat tinggal!)Sampai jumpa.
- Toodle-oo! - See you later, crocodile.
Sampai jumpa, buaya.
Maurice, my arm is tired. Wave it for me.
Maurice, tanganku lelah. Melambailah untukku.
Faster, you naughty little monkey.
Lebih cepat, monyet nakal.
By the time we get back to New York, it'll be the middle of winter.
Saat tiba di New York, tengah-tengah musim dingin.
So I was just thinking, why rush?
Jadi aku pikir, mengapa buru-buru?
Maybe we could make a few side stops along the way.
Kita singgah saja di beberapa tempat.
- Maybe Paris. - You just read my mind.
Mungkin Paris.!Kau baca pikiranku.
- l was thinking Spain. - Run with the bulls.
Spanyol.JLari dikejar banteng.
- What about Fiji? - Canada. Can we?
Atau Fiji?!Kanada. Bisa?
Cheap meds.
Pengobatan murah.
wouldn't even mind coming back here sometime.
Kuingin kembali ke sini suatu saat.
- l could do that. - You could say that again.
Aku mau.fAkupun mau.
- Skipper? - lalways wanted to go to Australia.
Skipper?!Aku ingin ke Australia.
Don't you think we should tell them that the boat's out of gas?
Katakan saja kapalnya kehabisan bensin.
Nah.
Tidak.
Just smile and wave, boys. Smile and wave.
Senyum saja dan lambaikan tangan kalian.